Okay, we are recording. He says he's available tomorrow.
Okay, fantastic. Yeah, so Charlie's recommendation. Try the point either he can
drop off at the T or give us a call.
I'll call him and find out what his story is, what his
schedule is. Okay. We are on פ"ח עמוד ב' Peh Chet Amud
Bet at the bottom.
We're still discussing this woman who has her husband has gone went
away to a kingdom by the sea
and now and one witness came and told her that he was
dead. She went and got married with the permission of בית דין
Beit Din and then her husband showed up alive and well. And
we said she has to leave both she has to leave her
new husband and her old husband. And now it says צריכה גט
מזה ומזה. tzericha get mizeh umizeh.
Does everybody see where we are?
One, two, three, four, five, six lines from the bottom.
So she needs a גט get from both husbands. בשלמא Bishlama says
the גמרא Gemara מראשון merishon
alright I understand that from the first husband she was legally married
she needs if she's not going to if she ever wants to
get remarried she needs to have
a גט. get. תיבעי גט tiba get אלא משני אמאי ela mishani
amai זנות בעלמא הוא. zenut be'alma hu.
This wasn't a marriage. She was married at the time when she
got married to him. There's no need for a גט get in
that case. It's adultery. It's just זנות. zenut. אמר רב הונא Amar
Rav Huna גזירה שמא יאמרו גירש זה ונשא זה ונמצאת אשת איש
יוצאת בלא גט. gezeira shema yomru gerish zeh venasa zeh venimtzeit eshet
ish yotza belo get.
So רב הונא Rav Huna says it's a גזירה gezeira decree of
the Rabbis because we're concerned that people will say that the first
husband divorced her she remarried the second husband and now there's a
way for wives to get out of marriages without a גט. get.
So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי ihachi סיפא דקתני seifa dektanei
אמרו לה מת בעליך ונתקדשה ואחר כך בא בעלה מותרת לחזור לו.
amru lah met ba'alech venitkadsha ve'acharkach ba ba'alah muteret lachazor lo.
So the continuation of the of the משנה Mishnah says that so
in our משנה Mishnah בית דין Beit Din told her that her
husband was dead and then and then he turned out to be
alive she went and got married and turned out to be alive.
In this case her husband they told her husband was dead and
she went and she only got she accepted קידושין kiddushin she only
became she only got she only got engaged she didn't actually consummate
the marriage. And in that case we say she's allowed to return
to her first husband. So we say התם נמי נימא גירש זה
וקידש זה ונמצאת אשת איש יוצאת שלא בגט. hatam nami neima gerish
zeh vekidesh zeh venimtzet eshet ish yotza shelo beget. People will say
oh why did she remarry she remarried because the first husband divorced
her and therefore she's leaving the second husband without a גט. get.
So we say לעולם בעי גט. le'olam ba'ei get. In that we
say actually when she leaves that first husband she actually does need
to get a גט get sorry when she leaves the second husband
she actually does need to get a גט. get. אי הכי ihachi
says the גמרא Gemara נמצא זה מחזיר גרושתו משנתארסה. nimtza zeh machzir
gerushato mishni'itrasa.
So the גמרא Gemara says well that doesn't help anything that she
needs that she needs a גט get because if you say that
then the same people who said oh she was divorced by her
first husband then she went to her second husband and our concern
is that they're going to think she's leaving her second husband without
a גט get even if you make her give her say that
she has to have a גט get now you have a case
of מחזיר גרושתו. machzir gerushato.
He is returning his divorcee the woman who he's already divorced once
she's been engaged
and that's only the position that the idea that you can do
that that you can return your divorcee from her engagement. Remember that
the law is that if you divorce your wife and then she
goes and marries someone else you're not allowed to remarry her. It's
a לאו. lav. It is yes.
So
but the question is well what if she didn't actually marry somebody?
What if she only accepted קידושין? kiddushin? So he says so there
is a position כרבי יוסי בן כיפור k'Rabbi Yose ben Kipur
maybe so we would think that the הלכה halacha the people will
think that the הלכה halacha is like כרבי יוסי בן כיפור k'Rabbi
Yose ben Kipur דאמר מן הנישואין אסורה מן האירוסין מותרת de'amar min
hanisuin asura min ha'eirusin muteret that you can't you can't remarry her
if she's already been married and consummated the marriage but if it's
just from an engagement you can remarry her and that's not the
הלכה halacha and we don't want people thinking that either. So we
say הא מדקתני סיפא אף על פי שנתן האחרון גט לא פסלה
מן הכהונה מכלל דלא בעיא גט. ha midektanei seifa af al pi
she-natan ha-acharon get lo pasla min hakehuna miklal delo ba'ya get.
Because it says at the end of that משנה, mishnah, that even,
excuse me, even if the last husband gave her a גט, get,
she's still not פסולה psula from the כהונה. kehunah. What does this
tell us? This tells us that she doesn't need a גט, get,
that whatever גט get that a husband gave—that the second husband gives
her isn't really a גט. get. Why? דאי בעיא גט, de'iba'ei get,
because if it was a real גט, get, if it was to
mean something, אמאי לא פסלה מן הכהונה? amai lo pasla min hakehunah?
Why wouldn't she be considered to be a divorcee in terms of
getting married to a כהן? kohen? אלא סיפא אמרי קידושי טעות הוו.
ela seifa amrei kiddushei taut havu.
What we assume is that people in the second case will say,
it wasn't, it was a mistake they, she took, she took the
money for the engagement by mistake. And therefore she gets out of
it without a גט. get. Nobody's gonna say that she can get
out of the engagement without a גט. get. So we say, that's
what we're saying, אמרי קידושי טעות הוו. amrei kiddushei taut havu. That's
what people—instead of assuming, right, the question is what are people going
to think? Instead of thinking this complicated thing that the first husband
divorced her and the second husband, whatever people think what is actually
the truth, which was it was קידושי טעות. kiddushei taut. She took
קידושין kiddushin without knowing that her husband was actually still alive.
So we say רישא נמי, reisha nami, if that's the case, in
the, in the initial case we should say אמרי נישואי טעות הוו.
amrei nisu'ei taut havu. In that case we should say that the
first case is also she was married in with a, by mistake.
So we say קנסו רבנן. kensu rabanan. One second, I'll just finish
this. So we say that the Rabbis punished her. So we say
okay, the Rabbis punished her in the first case, right, for going...
remember we said, we said
רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira said that from the חומרא chumra in the
end, the Rabbis were, were easy on her in the beginning, right?
And so this case, right, she went and got married with really,
she took a big risk and now the Rabbis punish her. So
we say סיפא נמי ליקנסוה. seifa nami liknesuha. So also in the
second case where she took קידושין kiddushin we should, we should punish
her, and we should say that she can't go back to her
first husband. We say רישא דעבדא איסורא, reisha de'avda issura, in the
first case where an actual event of adultery took place, that's a
case where קנסו, kensu, that's where they punish her. סיפא דלא עבדא
איסורא, seifa delo avda issura, but in the second case all she
did was she took some money from somebody and it looked like
she was going to have some kind of marital relationship with him,
but she didn't actually do anything that was אסור, assur, לא קנסו
רבנן. lo kensu rabanan. Yes,
I'm sorry. Strauss, this, this opinion of יוסי בן כיפר Yose ben
Kipar we're talking about? So we're still talking about the mistaken case
where the husband was away and come back. The case of יוסי
בן כיפר Yose ben Kipar is he would say that when we're
talking about a simple case of מחזיר גרושתו. machzir gerushato. That when
anybody divorces their wife, if she goes and she accepts a, engagement
from somebody else and then he comes back to her and he
gives her flowers and he says I'm so sorry, I don't want
anyone but you, and she says, oh, I want my first husband,
and she demands a גט, get, she gets a גט get from
the, from the person who she got קידושין kiddushin from, יוסי בן
כיפר Yose ben Kipar says that she can return to him. Everything
I have nothing to do at all with all this other stuff.
Yes, and our concern is that if you allowed this shenanigan to
go forward with, with the woman who got, whose husband was, was
dead and all of the confusion, that people will think that the
הלכה halacha is actually that way. And we say that's actually a
דעת יחיד, da'at yachid, that's not something that we, that we hold
by. And therefore it's a problem and so we have to sort
of avoid it.
Okay.
We say אין לה כתובה. ein la ketubah. She doesn't get a
כתובה ketubah from either husband.
מאי טעמא תיקנו לה רבנן כתובה? mai ta'ama tiknu la rabanan ketubah?
What was the whole point of a כתובה? ketubah? כדי
שלא תהא קלה בעיניו להוציאה. kedei shelo tehei kala be'einav lehotzi'ah. The
whole reason that we say that she gets a כתובה ketubah from
her husband is so that he won't be, he won't easily divorce
her. One second, Charlie. הא תהא קלה בעיניו להוציאה. ha tehei kala
be'einav lehotzi'ah. In this case we don't want to create any motivation
to prevent the husband from divorcing her. He needs to divorce her.
So of course we're not going to demand from him a כתובה.
ketubah. Charlie? This says תיקנו לרבנן כתובה. tiknu lerabanan ketubah. Isn't part
of the כתובה דאורייתא? ketubah de'oraita? No, I don't think so. The
כתובה ketubah is a, is a תקנת דרבנן. takanat derabanan.
Yeah, Dov?
But there's still a contract. There's a, what you mean then, the
Rabbis wanted to exclude this, they should've, they should've put some, a
clause in the contract of the כתובה ketubah saying and if, if
something should occur whatever
which, which would, such as this case or a more general clause,
then the כתובה ketubah is invalid. But once they establish the contract
and everybody agreed to the terms,
you know, it's more of a הפקר בית דין הפקר hefker beit
din hefker kind of... Yeah, it's an interesting, it's an interesting point.
What you said just put... it put me in mind for Charlie
that you might be thinking of a שטר קידושין. Shtar Kiddushin. Now
remember that she can get married דאורייתא De-oraita by way of a
contract, which is why it put me in mind, but the כתובה
Ketubah itself, that is to say that she has that she has
money, that he has that he has to pay her money on
divorce, is דרבנן. De-rabbanan. Is there not some part of the כתובה
Ketubah that says חזי ליכי מדאורייתא? Chazi lichi m'de-oraita?
That she has particular rights, right? שאר כסות ועונה. She'er, kesus, v'onah.
In the document of the כתובה, Ketubah, when the רבנים Rabbanim are
talking about the כתובה, Ketubah, they're talking about monies that he is
promised to deliver her.
In terms of the contract, that's an interesting point. You could say
that that's right. Like, this is a contract that's out in the
world and that really you just have to now once the contract
is made, you have to follow the terms of the contract. Or
you have to say the contract is made on the basis of
certain assumptions. The contract is not a contract that's entered into voluntarily
by both sides, or not entirely voluntarily. The contract is a required
contract that if you want to be married, you have to enter
into. In that case, you can say that the assumption of the
contract is that so long as the rabbinic mandate
for it to have the contract remains, the contract is valid. Once
there is no, once the reason for the contract is void, then
the contract itself is also void.
We are going to get down to הפקר בית דין הפקר Hefker
Beis Din Hefker not too long. Okay.
אין לה פירות ולא מזונות ולא בלאות. Ein lah peiros, v'lo mezonos,
v'lo blaos. So she doesn't have פירות peiros or מזונות mezonos and
בלאות. blaos. So when you, back when you did the משנה Mishnah
about יש מותרת לבעלה ואסורה ליבמה Yesh muteres l'ba'alah v'asurah l'yivama and
so on, there was the discussion of פירות. peiros. I don't remember
how, I know that Dov did it, I don't remember how detailed
he went into it. I'll just say very briefly, if you recall,
the case of פירות peiros is, it was on the board, okay,
and did the גמרא Gemara deal with it? And Dov? So
in the case of פירות, peiros, what happens is if a woman
marries a man who is not appropriate for her, like an אלמנה
לכהן גדול almanah l'kohen gadol or something like that, so she brings
in certain properties that belong to her that she will bring into
the marriage and she'll take out of the marriage. They're called נכסי
מלוג, nichsei milog, which I think you did say at the time.
I think I was here for that. However, the husband during that
time gets to eat the whatever profits those נכסים nechasim bring in.
Usually those נכסים nechasim are land and therefore either somebody, the husband
is working the land and taking פירות peiros off the land or
he's renting those lands, but whatever profits that brings, the husband gets
to spend that money.
But if it turns out that the marriage itself was never legitimate,
when they leave, when the woman then leaves the man, we say
that the husband has to pay her back whatever profits he received
from that land. That was the case of the אלמנה לכהן גדול.
almanah l'kohen gadol. In this case, she doesn't even get paid back
the money that the husband received from profiting from her נכסים.
nechasim. ולא מזונות, V'lo mezonos, and I'm sorry, and also not food
and also not the rags, right? Most of her clothes, well all
of her clothes are bought by her husband, but we general, the
general position is that the rags once she's worn them out belong
to her, but we say in this case she doesn't. David? It
seems to me that the רבנים Rabbanim aren't taking any responsibility for
allowing her to get into this position. Yes, that's correct. Or many
other cases there are strict guidelines if this is allowed, this is
not allowed. Here, they're allowing somebody to get into a position where
they're going to punish her. So if you recall, that's the discussion
that we had when רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira said משום חומרא שהחמירו
עליה רבנן בסופה הקילו עליה בתחלתה, mishum chumra shehichmiru aleha Rabbanan besofa
hikilu aleha betechilatah, right? Because of the, because they are creating, because
they're telling her that it's such a risk to go through with
this, they make it easy for her because essentially she should be
able to see what the risks are and she should be able
to do it only if she's very, very sure. So then the
גמרא Gemara said back on, this
was on דף ח Daf Ches or something like that. Anyway, they
said the גמרא Gemara says, well, don't make it easy on her
and don't make it harder on her, right? Just lay it straight,
lay it out in a very straightforward way and it's up to
her. שפיר עבדו רבנן דעבדו הכי. Shappir avdu Rabbanan d'avdu hachi. Okay,
so it's on דף ח, Daf Ches, right? Just do exactly what
you say. Tell her, make it just as difficult as it ought
to be and then have the punishment be just as reasonable as
it ought to be. And the גמרא Gemara itself says, no, we
actually have an ulterior motive for making it easier for her, which
is we don't want her to be an עגונה. agunah. And at
the end of the day, let's think to ourselves of what is
in terms of what really is the likelihood of this situation coming
up? Right? Your possibility is a woman whose
husband is
disappeared.
It's very important to be able to trust that, even though there
is a risk that things are going that bad things are going
to come of it, at the end of the day משום עגונה
אקילו בה רבנן. mishum agunah akeilu bah rabanan. So what I'm saying
is that I guess it I don't want to belabor it but
I agree with what you're saying so then it would seem to
me the rabbis then should take some compassion if in this unlikely
situation occurs and rather than taking responsibility, it's just laying it all
on her. It could be.
My impression is that, and and this is not to contradict what
you're saying, but my impression is that the way the rabbis are
at least I'm interpreting what you're saying to say like at least
she should get a כתובה. Ketubah. It's not her fault that this
happened. Who's going to take care of her now? Where's she going
to get funds? Right? But there is that opinion in the משנה,
Mishnah, it's just that we haven't talked about that. Right, that she
gets a כתובה. Ketubah. But
okay, but the people who say that she doesn't, so right, why
doesn't she? I would say that the גמרא Gemara here is viewing
the כתובה Ketubah as a motivator for the husband. They're saying it's
a kind of it is something that it's not support for the
wife. Support for the wife will come from her family, will come
from wherever it comes from. But what about this husband?
Are we going to put any kind of blocks in terms of
a כתובה? Ketubah? The purpose of the כתובה Ketubah is to prevent
quick and easy divorces.
Are we going to try to put blocks in order to prevent
a divorce in this case? Absolutely not. Because what we want is
for the husband to divorce her. Now that doesn't that doesn't eliminate
your point, but what it says is that the rabbis maybe more
even than we're expecting are not necessarily seeing things in a social
welfare kind of point of view. They're seeing things in a very
sort of
legalistic point of view that says the purpose of this is what
the motivations on the husband are going to be, not so much
what the what the wife is going to live on for the
rest of her life. But the first husband can't take her back
in anymore, right? That's right. So what difference the motivation? Is the
כתובה Ketubah No, the point is what if he doesn't want what
if he says I'm not giving her a גט get because I
don't want to give her a כתובה? Ketubah? What if we don't
want to turn
her into yeah I get that, but since he's obliged to he
doesn't want to be chained either, right? So he's obliged to divorce
her anyway. Oh, but he's not chained. Right? This is we've been
talking about Rivka Haut who used to used to sit in in
this שיעור, shiur, right? Oh, he was yeah. Oh, and those days
they what? In those days, right? If he wants he can he
can make this very a very difficult process. And considering how difficult
it is already, we're trying to grease the skids. Let's ask this
question a different way. What really do they expect the woman to
do? She has to investigate. How is she supposed to investigate? He's
off in some far off land. What what do they expect her
to do? So the case that we saw yesterday was a case
where she actually went ahead and married one of the witnesses so
he could be sure and he gave her signs. I suggested maybe
like a wedding ring or something. The husband never takes off this
ring. The only way you could get it off his finger is
if he were dead. So right,
in those in those situations, right, she could say maybe she you
know that would be enough of an investigation. I don't know, you
know this is this particular משנה Mishnah is one of the the
most troubling and difficult משניות. Mishnayot. Dov, did you have something? Yeah,
I just wanted to come back to Charlie's question. I was mistaken
about the clause of דחזי ליך מדאורייתא dechazi lach mid-Oraisa in the
כתובה Ketubah is actually referring to the dowry, the מוהר בתולות דחזי
ליך מדאורייתא. mohar betulot dechazi lach mid-Oraisa. But
and perhaps the end of the כתובה Ketubah deals with your question
Charlie which is וקביל עליו חתן דנן כחומר כל שטרי כתובות ותוספתות
דנהגין בבנות ישראל הצנועות כתיקון חכמינו זכרונם לברכה. achibel aloh chassan den
kichomer kol shtarei ketubos vetoseftos de-nahagin bivnos Yisrael hatzni'in ketikkun chachameinu zichronam
livrachah. דלא כאסמכתא ודלא כטופסי דשטרי. d'lo k'asmachta v'lo k'tofes d'shetarei.
In other words, it's done under the authority of the this this
כתובה Ketubah is done according to the authority of the rabbis. Right.
Right. But that clause doesn't necessarily no, but but but then it's
you know one could say perhaps one could say that that clause
kind of allows the rabbis to dissolve it just the same way
as they do the קידושין. Kiddushin. Right. Right. Okay.
So we say so we say
so she can't get these different things that she she normally gets
together with her כתובה. Ketubah. We say תנאי כתובה ככתובה דמי. Tenai
Ketubah ke-Ketubah dami. All of these things, מזונות, mezonot, food, all come
together with the כתובה. Ketubah. Once we're saying she doesn't get the
כתובה Ketubah it's also then that she doesn't get these things either.
נטלה מזה ומזה. Natlah mizeh umizeh. If she actually took something from
these from these husbands she has to return it. So we say
פשיטא peshita of course she has to return it doesn't belong to
her. מהו דתימא Mahu deteyma what would we have thought? כיון דתפסה
לא מפקינן מינה קא משמע לן. Keivan detafsa la mafkinan minah kamashma
lan. Since she got a hold of it, we generally, we often
have in cases where we're not certain we say, well if somebody
managed to get a hold of the thing that they're, that they're
arguing about, we don't take it away from them. And maybe that's
what we would think of think here, and we say, no, we
don't, she has to return it. Which gets back to David's point,
which is, okay, fine if you say that like we don't want
to in some way prevent the husbands from having motivation to divorce
her. But it is it's challenging to say that, well, but if
she somehow ends up with these things she has to return it.
Yep, I agree.
הולד ממזר Havlad mamzer and the whatever children she has from the
second husband or from the first husband if she goes back to
him
is a ממזר. mamzer.
Now we're going to get into something that's totally different. It's going
to take a while before we get back to סדר נשים. Seder
Nashim. We're going to go to סדר זרעים Seder Zeraim now.
תנן התם, Tenan hatam, is it sure that the ולד ממזר vlad
mamzer is from either of them? והולד ממזר מזו ומזו, Ve'havlad mamzer
mizu umizu, I think it says. Yeah, oh yeah, the משנה mishnah
absolutely says והולד ממזר מזו ומזו. ve'havlad mamzer mizu umizu. Right, but
when is it דאורייתא de'Oraita and when is it דרבנן, de'Rabbanan, right?
So we're going to talk about what exactly is the status, that's
exactly what we're going to get to, what's the status of this
ולד. vlad.
And it's actually the one who you think is off is worse
off is actually better off, the one who's the דרבנן de'Rabbanan one
is actually worse off.
Let's see what what I mean, it's going to take a while.
תנן התם, Tenan hatam, it says we have a משנה mishnah over
in מסכת תרומות. Masechet Terumot. אין תורמין מן הטמא על הטהור ואם
תרם בשוגג תרומתו תרומה במזיד לא עשה ולא כלום. Ein tormin min
hatamei al hatahor ve'im taram beshogeg terumato terumah bemezid lo asah velo
khlum. You cannot take תרומה terumah from טמא tamei stuff on טהור
tahor stuff. What's going to happen if you take תרומה terumah from
טמא tamei stuff? It's going to go to the כהן, kohen,
but he's going to have to burn it right away, it's not
going to be worth anything to him. So, but if you did
בשוגג beshogeg accidentally, it counts as תרומה. terumah. If you did it
במזיד bemezid on purpose, you didn't do anything. Says the גמרא, Gemara,
מאי לא עשה ולא כלום? mai lo asah velo khlum? If you
did it on purpose, what does it mean that you didn't do
anything? אמר רב חסדא לא עשה ולא כלום כל עיקר דאפילו האי
גריוא הדר לטבליה. Amar Rav Chisda lo asah velo khlum kol ikar
de'afilu hai griva hadar letivleh. You did nothing, that even the סאה
se'ah of תרומה terumah that you took, even that the stuff that
you took from
the טמא tamei area for the טהור tahor stuff, all of it,
even the תרומה terumah that you took is actually just טבל tevel
and you have to take תרומה terumah for all of it all
over again. רב נתן בר רב יהושע אמר לא עשה ולא כלום
לתקן את השירים אבל תרומה הוי. Rav Natan bar Rav Yehoshua amar
lo asah velo khlum letaken et hashirayim aval terumah havei. So by
taking this סאה se'ah of תרומה terumah from a טמא tamei basket,
you haven't done anything to
make the טהור tahor basket available to eat for yourself. But it's
still טבל. tevel. But the stuff that you took as תרומה, terumah,
that still counts as תרומה terumah and has to be burned. רב
חסדא לא אמר כרב ביבי בר רב יהושע דאי אמרת הוי תרומה
זימנין דפשע ולא מפריש. Rav Chisda lo amar keRav Bibi bar Rav
Yehoshua de'i amrat havei terumah zimnin depasha velo mafrish.
רב חסדא Rav Chisda doesn't give this answer that רב ביבי בר
רב יהושע Rav Bibi bar Rav Yehoshua says, that the טמא tamei
stuff is still תרומה. terumah. Why? Because if you say it really
is תרומה, terumah, then the guy might there'll be times when the
guy says, 'Look, I already took תרומה. terumah. How do I know?
Because you're telling me that this stuff is תרומה, terumah, it has
to be burned.' If that's the case then this stuff should already
be מתוקן, metukan, should be okay to eat, and he won't take
תרומה terumah a second time. That's why רב חסדא Rav Chisda doesn't
interpret it the way רב נתן Rav Natan says. Is there a
parallel that's why we say ממזר מזו ומזו? mamzer mizu umizu? We're
going to get there. We're going to discuss it but it is
it's going to, yes, you're four steps ahead but yes, okay.
So we say מאי שנא מהא דתנן, mai shna meha de'tenan, how
is this different, this case we're asking to רב חסדא, Rav Chisda,
from the משנה mishnah that says התורם קישות ונמצאת מרה אבטיח ונמצא
סרוח תרומה ויחזור ויתרום, hatorem kishut venimtzeit marah avatiach venimtza saruach terumah
veyachzor veyitrom,
שוגג shogeg sorry. So how is this different from somebody who takes
a קישות kishut to for
as תרומה terumah and it turns out to be a bad cucumber,
it's bitter, or a melon of some sort, it turns out to
be rotten?
So you say, what the stuff that you took, that is already,
that is תרומה. terumah. You have to do whatever you do with
תרומה terumah like do with תרומה, terumah,
but you have to go back and take more תרומה. terumah.
Wait, but does it mean my stuff was טבל? tevel? Mean like
for instance, I don't know, right, I buy a watermelon, I give
one to the כהן, kohen, I had no idea if it's good
or not, I mean to me it looked fine, and you know
and then I gave my מעשרות ma'asrot to the לוי, Levi, and
then I did everything I need to and start eating and they're
like, you know this watermelon really bad, am I eating טבל tevel
the whole time? But I don't know, I don't know the answer
to that. That's a good question. Maybe in the תוספות, Tosfos, I
didn't actually read through the תוספות. Tosfos.
But
yeah. It's a good question.
It's possible that it could you can I can imagine going either
way. One way is saying like look, you have to check your
תרומה. Truma. We're going to see later on they're going to say
that it's שוגג קרוב למזיד, shogeg karov lemeizid, that really he should
have tasted it. And then the תוספות Tosfos say how is he
supposed to do that? How are you supposed to taste it? The
תוספות Tosfos have an have a solution for it.
Gershon, you,
that's what they do in doing תרומה. Truma. But but
so either it's שוגג קרוב למזיד shogeg karov lemeizid and you're really
you really are in trouble, or we say it was שוגג shogeg
and so now למפרע l'mafrea you should take תרומה Truma now on
what you ate already. Now what about this tasting thing? What was
it you said the תוספות Tosfos say? All right, we'll see later
on the tasting thing that the תוספות Tosfos say what you should
do is you should take תרומה Truma from something that is you
know for sure is okay. If you want to take תרומה Truma
on a קישות, kishut, so you take תרומה Truma on a the
piece of the קישות kishut that you're going to cut off so
that you can taste it, then you taste it to make sure
that it tastes okay and then you give the rest of it
to the כהן Kohen as תרומה. Truma. That's their solution.
What you do is you cut off a piece of the the
it's all טבל, tevel, you cut off a piece of the cucumber
and you take תרומה Truma for that piece of cucumber, okay, and
then you taste it, make sure that it's okay, then you give
the rest of the cucumber to the כהן Kohen as תרומה. Truma.
Up, up.
It is interesting. So but the גמרא Gemara seems to think that
it is this is שוגג קרוב למזיד, shogeg karov lemeizid, so maybe
we would say that you're in trouble, or it's possible that we
would say that you can take תרומה Truma למפרע. l'mafrea.
So the question is רב חסדא Rav Chisda says right, we don't
tell somebody that that תרומה Truma that
the bad stuff that they took is תרומה Truma because what the
problem is sometimes they're going to be negligent and they're going to
say I already took תרומה Truma and they're not going to take
תרומה Truma a second time. So why in this case where you
gave a bad product do we say תרומה ויחזור ויתרום, Truma veyachzor
veyisrom, that you should go do תרומה Truma a second time? So
the גמרא Gemara says שוגג אמזיד קרמית. shogeg ameizid karamis. What's you're
comparing somebody who intentionally gave טמא תרומה tamei Truma to a כהן
Kohen who somebody who you can't trust for anything to somebody who
accidentally gave a bad cucumber to the כהן? Kohen? He wants to
give תרומה. Truma. He's somebody who's reliable. So we say שוגג לאו
עביד איסורא. shogeg lav avid issura. Right, the שוגג shogeg guy didn't
do anything that was אסור. assur. מזיד קעביד איסורא. meizid ka'avid issura.
So
there's
and therefore in a case of שוגג shogeg we can say תרומה
ויחזור ויתרום Truma veyachzor veyisrom because we can rely on this person
to really try to give תרומה Truma the proper way, whereas the
מזיד meizid he's already doing bad stuff so we don't trust him.
ורמי שוגג אשוגג. v'rami shogeg ashogeg. Okay, then let's do a case
of שוגג shogeg of a mistake with another mistake.
הכא קתני בשוגג תרומתו תרומה. hacha katani b'shogeg trumato Truma. In our
case we say that if he does it if he does it
by mistake, then it really is תרומה, Truma, this טמא tamei stuff.
התם קתני hasam katani תרומה ויחזור ויתרום. Truma veyachzor veyisrom. Okay, over
there if you when you give accidentally a bad cucumber to the
כהן, Kohen, it says it's תרומה Truma but you have to give
תרומה Truma a second time. Why in our case don't we say
if you did it by accident you should go back and give
תרומה Truma a second time?
שוגג, shogeg, oh I thought it was going to be further on,
here we are. שוגג קרוב למזיד. shogeg karov lemeizid. It's
this kind of שוגג shogeg that we're talking about in our case
is a mistake but really it's a mistake that you really ought
to have been taking care of. איבעי ליה למטעמי. ibai lei l'mitamei.
You really should have tasted it. And again, you can't taste טבל.
tevel. Okay, so that's the answer that's the answer that I gave
Michael when he when he asked, right?
תוספות Tosfos ask the question. תוספות איבעי ליה. Tosfos ibai lei. That's
right.
Right, they say that you cut off a piece of it, you
give you give תרומה Truma on that, taste it to make sure
it's okay, give the rest for
for for תרומה. Truma. So we say ורמי מזיד אמזיד. v'rami meizid
ameizid. Okay, so let's take the cases of doing it intentionally to
doing it intentionally. הכא קתני במזיד לא עשה כלום. hacha katani b'meizid
lo asa klum. Here we said if you did it by intentionally,
you didn't do anything. התם תנן hasam tnan התורמים משאינו נקוב על
נקוב hatoraim mishe'eino nakuv al nakuv תרומה ויחזור ויתרום. Truma veyachzor veyisrom.
So over
in again in מסכת תרומות Masechet Trumos we have a case where
what happens if you give תרומה Truma from a a flowerpot that
doesn't have holes in the bottom for a flowerpot that does have
holes in the bottom? What's the business with holes in the bottom
or not having holes in the bottom? If it if it has
holes in the bottom we consider it to be מחובר לקרקע mechubar
l'karka and it's חייב בתרומה. chayav b'Truma. If it doesn't have holes
in the bottom, then it's just a it's like you're growing it
in your window box
and it's not חייב בתרומה, chayav b'Truma, it's פטור. patur. So you've
taken something that doesn't really require תרומה Truma and you're trying to
make it תרומה Truma on something else.
So in that case we say תרומה ויחזור ויתרום. Truma veyachzor veyisrom.
In our case we said לא עשה ולא כלום. lo asa v'lo
klum. Right, if you did it on purpose.
We would think that it should be the same דין. din. So
the גמרא Gemara says בתרי מאני ציית ובחד מאנא לא ציית. bitrei
mani tza'at uvechad mana la tza'at. When you're dealing with two different
kinds of vessels, a vessel that has holes in it and a
vessel that doesn't have holes in it, people can understand and they'll
say, "Oh yeah, I see what you mean. I took it from
this one and I put it in that one. Okay, I'll give
תרומה Terumah a second time." But if you're dealing with a single
vessel, רש"י Rashi seems to explain that we're talking about two different
identical vessels,
so
if you're dealing with a single vessel, the guy'll say, "Look, what
difference does it make?
Right? This is טבל, tevel, this is טבל, tevel, I could take
תרומה Terumah from this to this, there's no difference between these two
things."
And therefore we say that's the basis of the difference. Now we
leave רב חסדא Rav Chisda and go on to רב נתן בר
אבי אושעיא. Rav Natan bar Abi Oshaia. ורב נתן בר אבי אושעיא
דאמר לא עשה ולא כלום לתקן שיריים אבל תרומה הוי. ve-Rav Natan
bar Abi Oshaia d'amar lo asa velo klum letaken shirayim aval Terumah
havei. He's the one who says that maybe so you haven't successfully
fixed your טהור tahor basket, but the stuff that you took still
is תרומה Terumah and needs to be burned. So we say מאי
שנא מהא דתנן mai shna me-ha ditnan מן הנקוב על שאינו נקוב
תרומתו תרומה ולא תאכל עד שיוציא עליה תרומה ומעשר ממקום אחר. min
ha-nakuv al she'eino nakuv terumato terumah velo tochal ad she-yotzi aleha terumah
u-ma'aser mi-makom acher.
So how is this different from a case where you took תרומה
Terumah from a flower pot that does have holes on a flower
pot that doesn't have holes, so something that is חייב chayav on
something that is פטור? patur?
So, right? How can you take תרומה Terumah on something that doesn't
require תרומה? Terumah? And yet, at the same time, we say
תרומתו תרומה, terumato terumah, right? It counts as תרומה, Terumah, ולא תאכל
עד שיוציא עליה תרומה ומעשר ממקום אחר. velo tochal ad she-yotzi aleha
terumah u-ma'aser mi-makom acher. You have to now take, you can't eat
that until you take more תרומה Terumah for it from another location.
One second.
Okay, so רש"י Rashi explains that the problem is that in this
case we say we still treat this תרומה Terumah as טבל, tevel,
right? You took, you took תרומה Terumah from the flower pot with
holes on the flower pot that doesn't have holes, and we
say okay since it doesn't require תרומה, Terumah, you have
essentially taken a section of טבל tevel out of your flower pot
with holes. In that case, you can't actually eat that or give
it to a כהן kohen to eat until you've taken תרומה Terumah
on it from another place. So what about our case? In our
case, we say that what you've given
this טמא tamei stuff to a כהן kohen and this כהן kohen
is going to think that this is תרומה טמא. Terumah tamei. תרומה
טמא Terumah tamei you have to burn, but what about but it's
not really תרומה טמא, Terumah tamei, perhaps, right? Maybe it's just טבל.
tevel. If it's just טבל, tevel, רש"י Rashi says you're not allowed
to just burn טבל, tevel, it's בל תשחית. bal tashchit. You can't
just burn food. So you're giving it to a כהן, kohen, a
כהן's kohen going to burn it. You have to figure out some
way to,
you have to treat it as טבל tevel also, you can't burn
it.
So why, so what's the difference according to רב נתן בר אבי
אושעיא? Rav Natan bar Abi Oshaia? So we say שאני הכא, shani
hacha, in our case it's different דמדאורייתא תרומה מעלייתא היא. de-mi-d'oraita terumah
me'alyata hi. That actually this טמא tamei תרומה Terumah is actually real
דאורייתא d'oraita תרומה Terumah and therefore we don't have to be concerned
when the כהן kohen burns it that it's not, that it's actually
טבל. tevel. כדירבי אילעאי, k'de-Rabbi Ilai, like the position of רבי אילעאי.
Rabbi Ilai. I'll just point out that the name of the of
the תנא tanna who is giving us this דין din is רב
נתן בר אבי אושעיא, Rav Natan bar Abi Oshaia, so it's pretty
reasonable to assume that he holds like רבי אילעאי. Rabbi Ilai. דאמר
רבי אילעאי d'amar Rabbi Ilai
מנין לתרום מן הרעה על היפה? minayin li-trom min ha-ra'ah al ha-yafah?
Except this might be רבי אילעאי התנא, Rabbi Ilai ha-tanna, sorry האמורא.
ha-amora. This isn't, he's not a תנא, tanna, so perhaps they're not
related at all. In any case, he brings a ברייתא, baraita, or
he sorry, he brings a מדרש, midrash, how do we know that
if you take תרומה Terumah from something that's bad on something that's
good, something low quality on something that's high quality, שתרומתו תרומה, she-terumato
terumah, that it counts as
תרומה? Terumah? דכתיב dich-tiv ולא תשאו עליו חטא בהרימכם את חלבו.
ממנו. ve-lo tisu alav chet ba-harimechem es chelbo mimenu.
You shall not carry a sin on it when you take the
best part of it, when you מרים, merim, when you take תרומה
trumah from the best part of it.
So the פסוק pasuk indicates that when you take תרומה, trumah, you
should be taking the very best. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואי
אין קדש נשיאת חטא למה. v’ee ein kodesh nesi'at cheit lama. If
what if when if it were the case that when you take
from low quality stuff to high quality stuff,
it isn't תרומה trumah at all, then what kind of a חטא
cheit is there in doing it? You haven't done anything. Right? There's
no legal implication to what you're doing. I was sitting last night
trying to think of an analogy in our law. I don't think
there is any analogy, but it does make sense. Right? If you
try to take תרומה trumah from something that you can't take תרומה
trumah from, that's not a חטא. cheit. We don’t say, oh, you'll
have a חטא cheit on you for trying to do that. You
haven't done anything. You still have to take if you eat it
without having taken more תרומה trumah you're in trouble, but having actually
taken the תרומה trumah is not a problem. So what what's the
basis of this חטא? cheit? The basis of the חטא cheit is
that you must have taken something that was low quality, it really
is real תרומה trumah and now you have a חטא cheit for
having taken low quality stuff for תרומה. trumah. Charlie. Is it a
ברכה לבטלה? bracha l'vatala? Yeah. So it could be a ברכה לבטלה.
bracha l'vatala. It could be a ברכה לבטלה. bracha l'vatala. The גמרא
Gemara doesn't go that way. The גמרא Gemara says if it's not
תרומה trumah at all, then then there's no then there’s no חטא.
cheit. Well, I think the point is you know, don't have you
won't transgress by eating it if you didn't take תרומה trumah from
it. You know what I mean, meaning like until you do, it's
טבל. tevel. So, you know, so you can't like you know in
other words What are you That's how you would interpret ואי אין
קודש נשיאות חטא למה? v'ee ein kodesh nesi'ut cheit lama? No, let’s
look at the פסוק. pasuk. That's a פסוק pasuk I would have
thought. Just the פסוק. pasuk. Oh, just the פסוק. pasuk. Yes. I
presume that the פסוק pasuk is talking about when I looked up
the פסוק, pasuk, it’s not it's certainly not talking about taking תרומה
trumah from the bad stuff to the good stuff. It's talking about
that you should remember to always give תרומה. trumah. Exactly. Right. That's
the that's what it's really talking about. But he’s reading it in
a different way. מכאן שהתורם מן הרעה על היפה שתרומתו תרומה. mikan
she’hatoraim min hara’ah al hayafah shetrumato trumah. And this is how we
know that taking תרומה trumah from bad quality stuff to good quality
stuff is still תרומה. trumah. אמר ליה רבה לרב חסדא. amar lei
Rabbah l’Rav Chisda.
Now we get into the now it gets starts getting complicated. רבה
Rabbah says to רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, לדידך דאמרת לא עשה ולא
כלום כל עיקר דאפילו ההיא גריבא הדר לטיבליה. l’didach d’amrat lo asa
v’lo klum kol ikar d’afilu ha’hu griva hadar l’tivlei.
So according to you, that you said that when it says you
haven't done anything, if you've taken תרומה trumah from טמא tamei stuff
onto טהור tahor stuff, talked so much about תרומה trumah we have
to remember our original case. That you haven't done anything if you
take תרומה trumah from טמא tamei onto טהור tahor and even the
תרומה trumah that you took from the טמא tamei stuff is itself
טבל. tevel.
מאי טעמא? mai ta’ama? And what's the reason that you say this?
גזירה דילמא פשע ולא מפריש. gezeira dilma pasha v'lo mafrish. Maybe you're
your concerned that if you call it תרומה, trumah, then the guy
will not take more תרומה trumah because he'll say, oh, I already
took תרומה, trumah, I don't have to take any more. מי איכא
מידי דמדאורייתא הוי תרומה ומשום דילמא פשע אפקעוה רבנן לחולין? mi ika
midi d'mide'oraita havi trumah umishum dilma pasha afkuha rabanan l’chulin?
How can it be possible that you have תרומה דאורייתא trumah de’oraita
and now the רבנן rabanan who are concerned that this fellow is
not going to take more
תרומה trumah have now taken this תרומה trumah and turned it back
into חולין? chulin? It can't be. וכי בית דין מתנין לעקור דבר
מן התורה? v’chi beit din matnin la'akor davar min haTorah? Can בית
דין beit din make a condition that will uproot something from the
תורה? Torah? All the time. All the time. As cases go. Yeah.
Interesting. I mean, I can can you give me an example? I
wouldn't think that בית דין beit din can. שב ואל תעשה. shev
v’al ta’aseh. There's always different, right? הפקר בית דין הפקר. hefker beit
din hefker. אפקעינהו רבנן לקידושין מיניה. afkinhu rabanan l’kiddushin minei. דמדאורייתא. d'mide'oraita.
Yeah, but that's not about
So okay,
we'll get into it. There are all kinds of reasons they’re different.
In the case of taking something that is תרומה מדאורייתא trumah mide’oraita
and turning it into חולין chulin and allowing anybody to eat it,
that’s a question for me. I don’t think I know of any
case that’s so blatant as that. But we are going to get
into it right now. Okay? And as I said, anyway, the ממזר
mamzer thing seems to be the thing. Okay. Well, as you said,
so that’s the whole reason that we have this entire piece here.
The reason that we’ve skipped over to מסכת תרומות masechet trumot is
because we're going to bring a case from ממזר. mamzer. אמר
ליה. amar lei. He said to to him, ואת לא תסברא, v’at
lo tisbera, right, like Charlie and Michael. What? You don’t think that
בית דין beit din has that power? והתנן הולד ממזר מזה ומזה.
v'hatnan havlad mamzer mizeh umizeh. The ולד vlad is a ממזר mamzer
from both of the both the husbands. בשלמא משני ממזר. bishlama mishani
mamzer. Okay, I understand, the second husband, any children from the second
husband, that’s a man who she slept with while she was still
married to the first husband. אלא מראשון אמאי? ela merishon amai? Why
should the ולד vlad from the first husband be a ממזר? mamzer?
אשתו היא. ishto hi. That's his wife. וישראל מעליא הוא v'Yisroel ma'alya
hu and he is a kosher ישראל. Yisroel.
וקשרינא ליה בממזרת. v'kashrina lei b'mamzeret. It's not when you make somebody
a ממזר, mamzer, you can't just say oh, it's לחומרא l'chumra we're
not going to, we don't have to worry about it. You know,
we're just telling him that he's, he's, he's a ממזר. mamzer. You've
actually created a new status and because he's a ממזר, mamzer, he
can go and he can marry a ממזרת. mamzeret. So, that's very,
very serious. אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said to him, רבה
Rabba to רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, הכי אמר שמואל, hachi amar Shmuel,
אסור בממזרת. assur b'mamzeret. He is actually אסור assur to a ממזרת.
mamzeret. In other words, this is truly a ממזר לחומרא. mamzer l'chumra.
He is אסור assur to marry ישראל, Yisroel, he's אסור assur to
marry a ממזרת. mamzeret. Can he marry a גיורת geyeret then or
something? I would expect that, I don't know, maybe he could marry
a גיורת. geyeret. I thought that he was really stuck.
Remember the ספק ממזר? safek mamzer? Right, so, right exactly. Although he's
not exactly but he's not exactly this person is not a ספק
ממזר. safek mamzer. It's not as clear as a ספק ממזר safek
mamzer can marry a ספק ממזר. safek mamzer. Right, because maybe one's
a ממזר mamzer and the other isn't. No, so maybe he could
marry a גיורת. geyeret. Yeah, yeah, because whatever he is, whichever status
he is.
Right, but this is a funny case because this isn't a ספק
ממזר. safek mamzer. This is a ממזר דרבנן mamzer d'Rabbanan that although
everybody knows that he's a ישראל לכל דבר, Yisroel l'chol davar, we're
going to call him a ממזר mamzer in order to punish his
mother
and not permit him to marry either a kosher Jew
or a ממזרת. mamzeret. I expect that a גיורת giyoret would be
okay. Is this
retroactive? This was very, this particular one is very painful to me.
It's very hard to understand.
You would think to punish her without punishing him. You would think,
you would think. Sins of the fathers on the children. Well, so
listen to what דוב Dov says.
דוב Dov says that ממזרות mamzeirus is all about, it's all about
punishing parents by using their children. לא יומתו אבות על בנים. lo
yumtu avos al banim. But this is painful. This is definitely painful.
So even if she gets a גט get from the second husband,
right? She's still not allowed. Yeah, yeah, and again only the case
where there was only one witness in the first. Yes, all of
this is a case where there was one witness. וכן, v'chein, and
the
same, and we notice it's not just שמואל. Shmuel. כי אתא רבין
אמר רבי יוחנן, ki ata Rabin amar Rabi Yochanan, אסור בממזרת. assur
b'mamzeret. So we have it both from בבל Bavel and from ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisroel. So
the גמרא Gemara says, ואמאי, v'amai, oh, sorry, this is the continuation,
no this is the גמרא. Gemara. ואמאי קרי ליה ממזר? v'amai karay
lei mamzer? Why do we call him a ממזר? mamzer? לאוסרו בבת
ישראל. l'osro b'bat Yisroel. We call him ממזר mamzer specifically in order
to keep him from marrying a בת ישראל. bat Yisroel. It says
here that he can marry another
ממזר דרבנן. mamzer d'Rabbanan. Yeah, great. So go find, go find, go
find one of those. He can also, he can also פרוזבול Prozbul
like כל דבר מן התורה kol davar min haTorah that they said
that you know, seven years is שמטה, shemitah, and then רבנן Rabbanan
say no, not really. But so they do, they do, yeah, they're
fine. פרוזבול Prozbul I think is a pretty good example.
So yes, I don't think they bring פרוזבול Prozbul here, but he's
going to, רב חסדא Rav Chisda is by no means done. He's
going to, he's going to try to bring as many examples as
he can, then when he's done the גמרא Gemara is going to
try to bring more examples. שלח ליה רב חסדא לרבה, shalach lei
Rav Chisda l'Rabba, right they went off on their own in their
own ways. רב חסדא Rav Chisda was from the בית דין Beis
Din of was from the ישיבה Yeshiva
of סורא, Sura, רבה Rabba was from the ישיבה Yeshiva of פומבדיתא.
Pumbedita. So they may have come together briefly, but at some point
they separate again. And then רב חסדא Rav Chisda continues to send
רבה Rabba proofs, רבה Rabba proofs. ושלח ליה רב חסדא לרבה v'shalach
lei Rav Chisda l'Rabba ביד רב אחא בר רב הונא. b'yad Rav
Acha bar Rav Huna. He says ואין בית דין מתנין לעקור דבר
מן התורה? v'ein beis din masnin l'akar davar min haTorah? What, you're
telling me that בית דין Beis Din can't uproot something from the
תורה? Torah? והתניא v'ha tanya מאמתי אדם יורש אשתו קטנה? me'eimatay adam
yoresh ishto ketanah? בית שמאי אומרים Beis Shammai omrim משיעמוד בקומתה mishetiamod
b'komatah ובית הלל אומרים v'Beis Hillel omrim משתיכנס לחופה, mishetikanes l'chuppah, רבי
אליעזר אומר משתיבעל. Rabbi Eliezer omer mishetiba'el.
So we know there's a case where a
if a father dies, the mother and the brothers can marry off
a young girl who's less than the age of majority to a
man with the condition that at the end when she reaches the
age of majority she can say, no, not into this husband, I'm
leaving, and leave without a גט, get, and she's still
כשרה kesherah to a כהן. kohen. It's as though she has done,
she's done nothing. The purpose apparently is the protection of this young
girl. In any case, if she's done nothing, can she marry a
כהן גדול? kohen gadol? I believe so, although I don't know. I
think that's right. Yeah.
In any case, she's not a בתולה. besulah.
She's so good question. I'm not, I'm not. You can't say she's
a בתולה betulah when she's not. Well, so I'm not sure whether
בתולה betulah is a physical fact or a or a legal a
legal fact. If it's about having been having belonged to someone, she
can't even marry a מוכת עץ mukat etz and we say that?
Did we? I don't know. We're going to see. We're going to
see in מסכת כתובות. Masechet Ketubot. קלו בתוליה, kalu betuleha, right? Meaning,
you know, okay, I don't I don't know the סוגיא, sugya, so
I don't know for sure.
In any case, so I don't know if she can marry a
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
In any case,
so now there's a husband, he has a a wife who is
a minor. Now, a husband normally can inherit his wife, but this
wife is a funny case because she could at a certain point
leave his house without ever without any kind and and take all
of her property with her.
So at what point is he permitted when if she were to
die, at what point would he be permitted to inherit her? So
בית שמאי Beit Shammai says when she kind of when she leaves
her minority her minority status, when she becomes
a a נערה, na'arah, right? כשעמדה על קומתה, keshe'amdah al komatah, רש"י
Rashi says with years and with hair. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. What's
the question? I'm sorry. The question is when can this husband if
the wife dies, when is the husband entitled
to to inherit her? Why not right away? He's her husband. Because
when she is because we could say, well, if she had lived
she wouldn't have stayed your husband, she would have left. So what?
She didn't leave. Well, because what that indicates is that the the
marriage actually doesn't have an official marriage status, it's a marriage דרבנן,
de-rabbanan, and her family can come and say this is our property.
Your marriage is not a real marriage. It's provisional, right? Because it
was never consummated. Says who? Perhaps the marriage I don't think I
don't think the marriage was never consummated, although that's a nice thought
I would like to believe that that were the case. Really? At
least that's one of the that's רבי אליעזר's. Rabbi Eliezer רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer has got yeah, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer gets this. רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, sorry. So meaning she still could have walked away
when she came of majority. Right. So let's say she's six years
old, whatever. Mm-hmm. So you have to wait six years and then
he can inherit her? Yeah. That's the position that's the position of
בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. And if she dies at six? If she
dies at six, בית שמאי Beit Shammai says the family inherits her.
So why would there even be a discussion? So what's this משעמדה
על קומתה? mishe'amdah al komatah? Oh, meaning he can't inherit her until
then when she dies? That's right. Okay, when she's meaning how old
does she have to be when she dies? That's right. Oh, okay.
Sorry, that that wasn't clear. Okay, faster.
Anyway, Rabbi Lindner gets to pick up the rest.
So בית הלל Beit Hillel says משתיכנס לחופה. mishetikanes le-chuppah. From the
time that they go into the חופה. chuppah. It's interesting exactly what
does בית הלל Beit Hillel mean? Does בית הלל Beit Hillel mean
the חופה chuppah that they go into when she is still a
minor? Do they have to go into the חופה chuppah again later
on? My expectation is בית הלל Beit Hillel means from the time
that they get married, this provisional from the time this provisional marriage
takes place, he has rights as a husband, like Michael said, until
she says I'm out of here.
And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says from the time when they consummate
the marriage, from the time when they when they actually sleep together.
So and then the משנה Mishna continues, the ברייתא braita continues, ויורשה
ומטמא לה ואוכלת בגינו תרומה. veyorshah umitama lah ve'ochelet bigino terumah. That
after these things he she he can inherit her, he can become
טמא tamei for her if he's a כהן, kohen, and she can
eat תרומה terumah based on being part of his household.
בית שמאי אומרים Beit Shammai omrim now that we're going to hear
have a little bit of a discussion in the גמרא Gemara based
on this ברייתא. braita. בית שמאי אומרים Beit Shammai omrim meaning תרומה
terumah she is not uprooting a תורה Torah prohibition if she's
a בת ישראל. bat Yisrael. So we're going to we're going to
discuss all of these different pieces.
בית שמאי אומרים משתעמוד בקומתה אף על גב דלא נכנסה לחופה. Beit
Shammai omrim misheta'amod be-komatah af al gav de-lo nichnesah le-chuppah. בית שמאי
Beit Shammai says even if she hasn't yet gone into the marriage
even she hasn't yet kind of had the official marriage ceremony, once
she's a נערה na'arah if they are engaged, the husband can inherit
her. אימא eima oh sorry that's a question. Is that the case
that she can that he can inherit her? אימא משתעמוד בקומתה ותיכנס
לחופה. eima misheta'amod be-komatah vetikanes le-chuppah. You have to have both that
they have gone through the official marriage ceremony and that she is
no longer a minor. והכי קאמרו
להו בית שמאי לבית הלל. ve-hachi ka'amru lehu Beit Shammai le-Beit Hillel.
And this is the point that בית שמאי Beit Shammai said to
בית הלל, Beit Hillel, דקאמריתו משתיכנס לחופה אי עמדה בקומתה מהניא לה
חופה ואי לא לא מהניא לה חופה. de-ka'amritu mishetikanes le-chuppah ei amdah
be-komatah mahanya lah chuppah ve-i lo lo mahanya lah chuppah. בית שמאי
Beit Shammai says to בית הלל Beit Hillel when does the חופה
chuppah actually take hold? Only if she's old enough for it to
to have actually have any kind of legal meaning. If she's too
young, then it's not a חופה. chuppah. I'm sorry, wait, so you
do a חופה chuppah with her again when she when she becomes
of age? Perhaps according to בית שמאי Beit Shammai you might have
to do חופה chuppah again, or you might say that retroactively if
you've already done חופה, chuppah, the the years will take care of
the
חופה. chuppah. רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer משתיבעל. mishetiba'el. רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says... is from the time that they sleep together the
first time. והא אמר רבי אליעזר אין מעשה קטנה כלום, Ve-ha amar
Rabbi Eliezer ein ma'aseh ketanah kelum, but רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said
that the actions of a קטנה ketanah don't count for anything.
אימא משתגדיל ותיבעל. Eima mishe-tagdil ve-tibaeil. So rather it must be that
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is going in the line of בית שמאי
Beis Shammai once they have sex having her when she's already become
a when she's no longer a minor. Now we're going to get
into the question of uprooting things from the תורה. Torah. דתניא מיהת
יורשה. De-tanya mihat yorshah. But we know at least that this husband
can inherit her.
והא הכא דמדאורייתא אבוה ירת לה ומדרבנן ירת לה בעל. Ve-ha hacha
de-midoraisa avuh yaris lah u-miderabanan yaris lah ba'al. From according to the
position of בית הלל Beis Hillel at least this is a
דרבנן derabanan marriage. מדאורייתא Midoraisa her family has the rights to her
property and yet the Rabbis are coming along and saying that the
husband should inherit her. Dope. Property of this young... she
might have she might have all kinds of... she's an orphan. No,
she
could have she could have inherited if this whole marriage rabbinic and
the brother and the mother do it. Oh she has no if
she doesn't have any brother then she may have inherited. Yeah, who
says?
Can just the mother alone marry her off? Yeah, I think so.
Rabbinic would be the mother and a brother. No, it doesn't have
to be both of them, it's one or the other. I think
the mother alone can do it. I think so. That the mother
can do it.
I think it must be a male... I don't know, but the
mother can definitely do it. She can? Alone? Yeah. Okay, I'll take
Charlie's word for it.
In any case the
she could have property she could have property that her father gave
her you know in preparation as her as her dowry. She has
נכסי מלוג nichsei milug the same as any other woman can have
נכסי מלוג. nichsei milug.
So we say הפקר בית דין היה הפקר. hefker beis din hayah
hefker. בית דין Beis din can declare monies... no... you know, the
mother or the brother. So הפקר בית דין היה הפקר, hefker beis
din hayah hefker, בית דין beis din can declare property to be
הפקר hefker and they can move it around to whoever they want.
דאמר רבי יצחק מנין שהפקר בית דין היה הפקר. De-amar Rabbi Yitzchak
minayin she-hefker beis din hayah hefker. How do we know that this
principle is true? שנאמר כל אשר לא יבוא לשלושת הימים בעצת השרים
והזקנים יחרם כל רכושו והוא יבדל מקהל הגולה. She-ne'emar kol asher lo
yavo li-shloshet ha-yamim ba-atzat ha-sarim ve-ha-zekenim yachoram kol rechusho ve-hu yibadel mi-kehal
ha-golah. So in Ezra it says that anybody who doesn't show up
on the third day according to the order of the שרים sarim
and הזקנים ve-ha-zekenim meaning presumably the בית דין, beis din, their property
will be declared null and void it'll be confiscated and they will
be separated out from the from the people. He's pointing out that
the פסוק pasuk from the נביא navi is considered good enough to
be דאורייתא. de-oraisa. This isn't even from the נביא. navi. This is
from Ezra. Right, so writings, whatever. So it's interesting to try it's
an interesting study and I believe people have done it in terms
of what does the גמרא Gemara use פסוקים pesukim for. In this
case presumably the פסוק pasuk is not being used to prove that
this is the way that God intended it, but this is used
to prove that in that Ezra we can rely on the fact
that Ezra is not breaking the הלכה halacha and look Ezra was
able to do this, סימן siman that בית דין beis din can
do it. So it's more of a precedence issue than a textual
proof issue if that makes any sense. It's not quite the same
as what we said above when we said ולא תשאו עליו חטא
בהרימכם את חלבו velo tisa'u alav chet be-harimchem et chelbo. ממנו. mimenu.
Right there we were using the פסוק pasuk to try to delve
to try to derive out a הלכה. halacha. Here we're simply seeing
an example of הפקר בית דין היה הפקר hefker beis din hayah
hefker in the תנ"ך Tanach and we assume that these people were
doing it right. רבי אלעזר אמר מהכא. Rabbi Elazar amar me-hacha. רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar has a different place. אלה הנחלות אשר נחלו אלעזר
הכהן ויהושע בן נון וראשי האבות למטות בני ישראל. Eleh ha-nechalot asher
nichalu Elazar ha-Kohen vi-Yehoshua bin Nun ve-rashei ha-avot le-matot Bnei Yisrael. So
now here's a case where we are going to derive it. He
takes a he brings a פסוק pasuk from יהושע Yehoshua and it
says that who inherited the the property to בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael,
אלעזר הכהן יהושע בן נון Elazar ha-Kohen Yehoshua bin Nun and ראשי
האבות למטות בני ישראל. ve-rashei ha-avot le-matot Bnei Yisrael. וכי מה עניין
ראשים אצל אבות? Ve-chi mah inyan rashim etzel avot? Why does it
say ראשי אבות rashei avot the heads of the fathers? So what's
the what's the connection? אלא לומר לך מה אבות מנחילים בניהם כל
מה שירצו אף ראשים מנחילים את העם כל מה שירצו. Ela lomar
lecha mah avot manchilim beneihem kol mah she-yirtzu af rashim manchilim es
ha-am kol mah she-yirtzu. So right here we're not saying oh they
did it properly and we can take this as precedence. Here we
really are using the נביא navi as a פסוק pasuk to derive
out. Okay ראשים rashim which is the בית דין beis din are
similar to אבות. avot. How are they similar? Because they can essentially
do inheritance however they choose. ומטמא לה U-metame lah says the says
the גמרא Gemara and he becomes טמא tame for her. another case
of בית דין *Beit Din* being עוקר *oker* something from the תורה
*Torah*. דהא הכא דמדאורייתא אביה ומתמא לה ומדרבנן ומתמא לה בה *Deha
hacha demidoraita avia umitemila umiderabbanan umitemila bah*. So דאורייתא *D'oraita*
only her father should be able to get become tamei for, but
in this case the בעל *ba'al* is משום דהויא לה מת מצוה
*mishum dehavya lah met mitzvah*. So we say it's she's actually a
מת מצוה *met mitzvah*. So say ומי הוי מת מצוה *umi havei
met mitzvah*? What? All of a sudden she has that she's a
מת מצוה *met mitzvah*? מת מצוה *met mitzvah* is somebody who doesn't
have anyone to bury them, right? והתניא *vehatanya*, here's the ברייתא *braita*.
איזהו מת מצוה *eizehu met mitzvah*? What is a מת מצוה *met
mitzvah*? כל שאין לו קוברים *kol she'ein lo kovrim*. קורא ואחרים עונים
אותו *Korei veacherim onim oto*, אין זה מת מצוה *ein zeh met
mitzvah*. Somebody who doesn't have anyone to bury them. If you call
out and you say help bury somebody, where are the relatives to
help bury this person, and people say oh I'm over here, that's
not a מת מצוה *met mitzvah*.
So we say הכא נמי *hacha nami*, כיון דלא ירתי לה *keivan
dela yarti lah*. This is incredible. Because the רבנן *rabbanan* have created
this situation where הפקר בית דין הפקר *hefker Beit Din hefker*, they've
taken away her property from the family. The family says okay, we
can't get any property from her anymore. In that case, bury you
bury her, we don't we're not going to bury her. So since
there's they've their her family is not going to inherit her, they're
just going to leave her corpse to decay. Well no, they're going
to rely on the husband to do it. She's a מת מצוה
*met mitzvah*. קריא ולא ענו לה *Karya velo anu lah*, קריא ולא
ענו לה *karya velo anu lah*, right? The husband can call out
and say go come bury your daughter and they say look you
have her property, you bury her. Pretty mercenary.
It's rough. It's rough, I have to say. The last one, ואוכלת
בגינות תרומה *veochelet beginot terumah*, בתרומה דרבנן *biterumah derabbanan*. So what kind
of תרומה *terumah* does she eat? תרומה דרבנן *terumah derabbanan* reasonable for
a marriage דרבנן *derabbanan*. And we'll leave it there. It's been a
pleasure. Does anybody know what the civil law is? I found another
חילוק *chiluk*. The mother can't bury. Does anybody know what the civil
law is? The situation with the husband or the woman who dies
or anybody who dies based on the idea of the spouse. Good
idea. Good idea. I'm just saying this is the rough thing about
this דף יומי *Daf Yomi* is that no, it's every day.
You first figure that out, huh?